ELDIN SAHBAZ

Denver, Colorado, USA +1 (607) 597-9607 | sahbaz.eldin@gmail.com linkedin.com/in/eldinsahbaz | github.com/eldinsahbaz

SUMMARY

Program Manager and Data Scientist with ~8 years of proven success delivering key business objectives. Established and scaled transformative, enterprise—level, Digital Transformation initiatives across the Petroleum and Semiconductor industries. Enabled Data Science's 65% AI/ML market share across all business functions within British Petroleum's US onshore O&G division and independently produced US\$997MM in value. Delivered patent—pending AI—powered computational chemistry solutions — valued at US\$500M+ annually — for INFICON's Semiconductor business.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Program Manager

British Petroleum (BP)

November 2023 – Present

Denver, Colorado

- · Directed and executed Data Science and ML Engineering Digital Transformation strategies achieving 45% market share in Exploration & Development and enabling the team's 65% overall market share across the organization.
- $\cdot \ \, \text{Managed and deployed the Long-term Production Risk Assessment Simulation application for Reservoir Engineering}.$
- $\cdot \ \, \text{Oversaw the AWS migration efforts for the } \textbf{Salt Water Disposal} \ \text{and } \textbf{Productivity Index} \ \text{PowerBI reports}.$

Senior Data Scientist

British Petroleum (BP)

February 2023 – Present Denver, Colorado

- Generated US\$977MM in revenue for the Bone Spring formation with a well development plan NPV of US\$700MM,
 Drilling & Completions cost reductions of US\$250MM, and core collection cost avoidance amounting up to US\$27MM
 launching AI Lithofacies Prediction and enabling regional fluid mobility and reservoir quality assessments.
- Drove **US\$20MM annually** in value for Reservoir Engineering's EOR program productionalizing the **ML Refracturing Estimator** with Streamlit and yielding a **500% enhancement** to the stakeholders' well prospecting process.

Data Scientist

INFICON

June 2018 – February 2023 Syracuse, New York

- · Directed the Automated Sensor Calibration development program for semiconductor sensor technologies delivering patent—pending advances and driving annual cost reductions forecasted in excess of US\$500M.
- · Led cross–functional efforts defining mathematical foundations for signal processing algorithms and designed A/B tests via SciPy.stats and Nolds delivering a 21% increase in sensor fidelity using SciPy.optimize and Statsmodels.
- · Invented the Bijective Neural Architecture for density estimation via PyTorch yielding a 95% increase in accuracy.
- · Established KPIs and executed simulation A/B tests with synthetic chemical data built using PySwarms, SciPy.optimize, SciPy.stats, and SciPy.integrate attaining 50% coverage across chemical detection and monitoring systems.

Research Assistant

Syracuse University | Data Lab

 $June\ 2017-August\ 2017$

 $Syracuse,\ New\ York$

· Modeled social media engagement metrics, formulating repeated measures experiments, utilizing Scikit-learn and NLTK.

Technology Analyst

JPMorgan Chase & Co.

June 2016 – August 2016

Jersey City, New Jersey

· Developed project business cases alongside senior team members and **deployed code** to live internal JPMC applications.

Software Engineer

Self-employed

June 2015 – September 2015

 $Syracuse,\ New\ York$

· Engineered information retrieval systems for **British Petroleum** and local government clients as a subcontractor.

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Syracuse University | Hosein Research Group

August 2014 – May 2015

 $Syracuse,\ New\ York$

· Awarded the **Dean's Leadership Grant** supporting simulation studies quantifying energy loss across solar cell surfaces.

PATENTS & PUBLICATIONS

Method of Auto Tuning One or More Sensors USPTO Application 18/686,753

February 2024 Patent Pending

INVITED PRESENTATIONS

Neural Attention for Seismic Data Processing

BP Geophysics R&D Seminar

July 2024

Improving Mass Spectrometry Signal Fidelity

INFICON Data Analytics Summit

November 2020

Automatic Text Summarization — Deep Learning & Classical Approaches

Syracuse University iSchool Poster Session

April 2018

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Core Analysis Workshop

April 2024/December 2023

UT Austin Bureau of Economic Geology

Advanced Power BI — Power Query and DAX

April 2023

Havens Consulting

Machine Learning for Model Predictive Control & Process Analytics

Dr. S. Joe Qin, President of Linguan University

June 2019

HONORS & AWARDS

Graduate Merit Scholarship

August 2017 - May 2018

Syracuse University

Summa Cum Laude

May 2017

Syracuse University

The Warren Semon Prize

May 2017

Syracuse University

Dean's Leadership Grant

September 2014

Syracuse University

Dean's List

August 2014 - May 2017

Syracuse University

The Founders' Scholarship

August 2014 – May 2017

Syracuse University

EDUCATION

Tools

Syracuse University

May 2018

Master of Science | Computer Science

Syracuse University

May 2017

Bachelor of Science | Computer Science

Summa Cum Laude

SKILLS & COMPETENCIES

Business Strategy, Business Development, Stakeholder Management, Agile Project Management, CRISP-DM

Technical Artificial Intelligence, Deep Learning, Transfer Learning, Machine Learning, Linear & Nonlinear Modeling,

Numerical Optimization, Regression, Classification, Statistics, Probability, Time Series, Statistical Signal

Processing, Data Collection, Data Preprocessing, Data Analysis, Data Wrangling, Data Mining

AWS SageMaker, Linux, Git, Python, PyTorch, Scikit-learn, Pandas, SciPy, Statsmodels, NumPy, NLTK, Gensim, OpenCV, Seaborn, Matplotlib, SLB Techlog